I cannot tell you the joy I have right now, joy that I have not felt in many, many weeks,
but the joy that I feel right now in your company, the joy in being able to gather
with a testament to our ancestors, with a testament, a commitment to the generations after us,
that we are fighting, that we fought for our humanity, that we were here,
that we said no, that we gathered, that we had no fear.
I am so happy to be with you here, with the folks in the Riverside Church,
with the folks that are streaming with us.
When I thought about this evening, I did not know if I should speak to you as a teacher
and tell you about Gaza, Gaza.
Should I tell you that Gaza was once a city district of historic Palestine
that sits on the eastern coast of the Mediterranean Sea,
that its harbor and fertile land has made it a focal point of trade and empire for centuries,
including the Romans, the Mongols, and Napoleons' France,
that prior to 1948, the Gaza district contained almost 90 towns and villages.
It was 38 times larger than the current 140 square mile strip,
making it the largest district in mandatory Palestine
until Zionist militias destroyed a majority of these towns.
Should I tell you that upon Israel's establishment,
a severely truncated Gaza absorbed nearly 25% of Palestinian refugees
exiled from their former homes,
increasing its population from 80,000 to 280,000,
that that number has grown to 2.2 million today
who are predominantly refugees and children dependent on food aid for survival?
Do I explain to you that Israel began to circumscribe this Palestinian territory in 1993
as it was entering into the Oslo Peace Accords,
that it began a process of de-development, isolation, containment of Gaza
with the intent to make it a Palestinian state-led
and to instead focus on annexing the West Bank
whose land it coveted and whose natives it also sought to remove?
In this context, I can tell you that Israel imposed a land siege and a naval blockade,
hermetically sealing this coastal enclave,
placing it on a subsistence diet just above starvation,
relegating it to conditions of bare life,
and then systematically pummeling it with advanced weapons technologies
in a bid to take the land without the people,
to achieve in Gaza by warfare
what it seeks to do in the West Bank through martial law,
in East Jerusalem through administrative law,
and throughout historic Palestine through civil law.
Or should I speak to you as an attorney
and tell you that when Israel withdrew its settlers and military infrastructure in 2005
that it maintained its effective control over the population registry,
the skies, the underground water sources,
the electromagnetic spheres,
all points of ingress and egress,
and thus remains in occupying power
with the duty to protect its civilians,
that Israel has no right to self-defense against territory that it occupies.
Has no right to self-defense against territory that it occupies
no more than Portugal had the right to self-defense
to protect its hold on Mozambique and Angola.
Should I explain that people fighting against colonial domination,
alien occupation, and racist regimes,
Palestinians have a right to use armed force
so long as it's regulated by the laws of war?
Would it be helpful to tell you
that any force must be bound by principles of distinction and proportionality
and that Israel has promised to disavow both?
Its top military and political brass have made clear
that their purpose is destruction, not accuracy.
There are no Palestinian civilians,
that hospitals and schools and sources of electricity and fuel
are not afforded the presumption of civilian infrastructure.
Do I remind you
that they have expressed a specific intent
to destroy in whole or in part a people
based on their racial, ethnic, national, or religious grounds?
Should I remind you
that they need not kill a single person
in order to be prosecuted
for the crime of intent and incitement
according to the Genocide Convention?
Should I recite the numbers anyway
that in 26 days, Israel has killed more Palestinians
that were murdered in the Bosnian genocide?
Do I tell you that for the past two decades,
Israel has not gotten away with murder,
but has changed international law
to make its grotesque violence permissible?
That it says Gaza is not occupied, nor is it its sovereign.
It is a hostile entity.
That it claimed that this is not a civil war,
nor is it an international armed conflict,
but it's this new category,
an armed conflict short of war.
That Palestinians participating in hostilities
are not merely legitimate targets when they pick up arms,
but even when they lay asleep next to their partners
in homes filled with their families.
That the lives of their soldiers
are worth more than the lives of enemy civilians,
and proportionality is forward-looking,
so that untold destruction is reasonable
and recommended in the language of law.
Do I remind you all that what happens to Palestinians now
sets a new precedent
that means that everywhere, anywhere in the globe
is not safe?
No, no, no, no, no.
I should speak to you plainly as a mother.
I should tell you
that my heart breaks
over and over
every single day.
That I cannot
take
another
image
of a baby
covered in dust
from the rubble that was her home
gasping for air.
That I cannot handle
another young girl
running after her mother,
her mother's corpse,
asking her
to get up.
Qumi yamma.
That it pains me
to watch
a young boy
begging
the man about to bury
his baby brother
for a strand of hair
from his baby brother's head.
That I have to admit
that I am in sheer awe
of Wa'il Dahduh
who buried
his wife
and his son
and his daughter
who both wanted
to be journalists
like him
and got up
the next day
in front of a camera
to continue
to report
the genocide
of his people.
Shall I describe
my acute stress
imagining
130 newborns
in NICU
at risk of death
because of lack
of fuel
and electricity
only to look up
and hear anchors
ask me
if the price
is worth paying
because some
civilian life
is sacred.
Or that when I
ask my cousin
in Ramallah
this morning
how her children
are faring
she says
they have learned
a painful lesson
these past weeks
that world powers
agree that their lives
are not worthy.
Do I speak to you
as a Palestinian
and tell you
that we
are a remarkable
people
fighting
for the noble
cause
of freedom?
That we
understand clearly
that this is a
genocidal campaign
intended to complete
the Nakba
to fulfill
the Zionist fantasy
of a land
without a people
despite a valiant
people
that refuse
to disappear
who vow
to stay in their
homes rather than
become refugees
again
who tell us
whose pride
and love
and rootedness
and tradition
and song
and prayer
and belonging
will forever
forever
haunt settlers
who build nuclear weapons
marshal global
superpowers
and still tremble
before the truth
of our existence.
We existed
before Zionist
colonial invasion.
We exist now
even among the rubble
of humanity's remains.
We will exist
when Zionism
is dismantled
bit by every racist
colonial bit.
Let me speak to you
let me speak to you
as a comrade
and tell you
that we must fight on
that we must rest
and breathe
and not tire
that our efforts
are causing global
vibrations
and generational change
filling streets
from London
to Cairo
Amman
to Beirut
Istanbul
to Sana'a
shutting down Congress
shutting down
Grand Central Station
Highway 101
in San Francisco
having a State Department
official resign
a UN
Human Rights Officer
resign
having Chile
Columbia
and Jordan
rescind their ambassadors
watching Bolivia
cut its diplomatic ties
listening and witnessing
2,000 plus
black allies
signing on to a letter
in Palestine
when 3 million
Belgian unionized workers
refused to transport
Israeli weapons
We have disrupted
Senate appropriations
hearing
asking for more money
We have watched
hundreds of artists
call for a ceasefire
and poll 66%
of Americans
that oppose
this genocide
and call for a ceasefire
now
that number keeps growing
and as your comrade
I want to ask you
and remind you
that as we fight on
to be vigilant
because repression
is growing
to remind you
that
in our vigilance
we can protect ourselves
we need not cower
Palestine Legal
the only legal institution
in the United States
dedicated
to protecting activists
and allies
in order to keep fighting
has documented
400 incidents
of harassment
abuse
doxing
in the past
three weeks alone
on average
annually
they document
200 to 300 incidents
but in the past
three weeks
400 incidents
alone
law students
who had
their offers rescinded
medical residents
who have been fired
editors-in-chiefs
of art magazines
who have been fired
fashion magazine
or excuse me
entertainment agency
executives
who have been set aside
for opposing genocide
and while this racist
warmongering media
and political establishment
has led to the stabbing
of a six-year-old
Waleed Fayyumi
26 times
in his home
in Illinois
Allah irhamak
and the murder
of a Muslim woman
in Texas
Allah irhamak
the Biden administration
is mobilizing law enforcement
to surveil
social media
of university students
struggling
for Palestinian liberation
and what happens
I do it
if it's not
꺑
I don't think
I'm just
going back
again
to be
ak
want
to
you
hang
on
and
you
have
found
in
you
and